Guide to the Muslims in Brooklyn oral histories 2018.006
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Oral History Interview with Mohammed Hashem, May 10, 2018; 2018.006.18
  Bangladesh; Bangladesh -- History -- Revolution, 1971; Bangladeshis -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Food -- Social aspects -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islamic education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Police-community relations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Political activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Kensington (New York, N.Y.); Bangladesh Muslim Center and Islamic School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Hashem, Mohammed
- Oral History Interview with Debbie Almontaser, May 14, 2018; 2018.006.19
  Debbie Almontaser was born in Yemen. Her family immigrated to the United States when she was a toddler and settled in Buffalo, New York. She married her husband and moved to the Cobble Hill neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1980. Her involvement with her child's primary school inspired her to pursue a career in education, eventually becoming the founding principal of the Khalil Gibran International Academy in Brooklyn. She also became a prolific activist, including coordinating New York City's first Arab-American Heritage Week in 2005; founding the Bridging Cultures Group, Inc. in 2015; supporting Democratic nominee Hillary Clinton's 2016 presidential campaign; and organizing the Yemeni Bodega Strike at Brooklyn Borough Hall in 2017. Throughout her work as both an educator and an activist, she put significant focus on multicultural and interfaith partnerships, also founding and participating in a number of groups and initiatives aimed at increasing empathy across racial, ethnic, and religious lines. She earned a bachelor of the arts in English and world religions from St. Francis College in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn; a master of the sciences in multicultural education and reading from Adelphi University in Manhattan; and a doctor of education in urban education and leadership from Fordham University in the Bronx.
  In this interview, Debbie Almontaser discusses the aftermath of her resignation as principal of the Khalil Gibran International Academy in Brooklyn, including successfully suing the city for violating her right to free speech and discriminating against her for her Muslim faith and Arab heritage; experiencing a subsequent outpouring of community support; and successfully defending herself against a retaliatory lawsuit by the city alleging defamation. She also speaks about the 2016 presidential election, especially regarding her support for Democratic nominee Hillary Clinton; her speech at the Democratic National Convention in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; and her community's reaction to Republican nominee Donald Trump's victory. In addition, she elaborates at length about increased activism among Yemeni New Yorkers in the wake of the Trump administration's Executive Order 13769 (colloquially known as "the Muslim ban"), including coordinating the Yemeni Bodega Strike with businessman Zaid Nagi at Brooklyn Borough Hall in 2017 and serving as board secretary with the Yemeni American Merchants Association. Debbie Almontaser was also interviewed on February 10, 2018 for this collection. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  Actions and defenses |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organization -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Demonstrations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islamophobia -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Jewish-Arab relations; Muslim Americans -- Press coverage; Patriotism -- United States; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 2016; Women in Islam -- New York (State) -- New York; Women political activists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Yemeni Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Yemeni Bodega Strike (2017); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Yemeni American Merchants Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); New York (N.Y.). Board of Education; Almontaser, Debbie; Nagi, Zaid
- Oral History Interview with Syeda Akter, May 22, 2018; 2018.006.20
  Syeda Akter was born in 1965 in East Pakistan (now Bangladesh). She immigrated to the United States to join her husband after their marriage. They initially settled in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn, and then moved to the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn to raise their family. She co-founded the Brooklyn chapter of Desis Rising Up and Moving (DRUM), an activist organization aimed at empowering South Asian New Yorkers, became involved in a local ladies' club, and also spent many years working for small medical practices doing both office work and basic medical procedures.
  In this interview, Syeda Akter discusses her upbringing in Bangladesh, following her husband to the United States, and her entry into the medical field. She also speaks about working while being her children's primary caregiver, her commitment to her children's education, and friction over her personal thoughts on religious teachings. In addition, she talks about her friendship with Annie Ferdous (interviewed on May 25, 2018 for this collection), their involvement with a local ladies' club, and co-founding the South-Asian and Indo-Caribbean-led Desis Rising Up and Moving (DRUM). Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Arranged marriage -- Bangladesh; Bangladesh; Bangladeshis -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Child rearing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam -- Customs and practices; Islamic education of children -- New York (State) -- New York (State); Medical assistants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim families -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women in Islam; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.); Kensington (New York, N.Y.); Bangladesh Institute of Performing Arts (Queens, New York, N.Y.); Desis Rising Up and Moving (Queens, New York, N.Y.); Akter, Syeda; Ferdous, Annie
- Oral History Interview with Annie Ferdous, May 25, 2018; 2018.006.21
  Annie Ferdous was born in 1959 in East Pakistan (now Bangladesh). She had a strong foundation in both education and dance from an early age, ultimately earning a master's degree in political science from the University of Dhaka in Bangladesh and performing on stage in Bangladesh, England, and the United States. She immigrated to the United States with her husband shortly after their marriage. They settled in the Kensington neighborhood of Brooklyn, where she founded the Bangladesh Institute of Performing Arts and became involved in a local ladies' club.
  In this interview, Annie Ferdous discusses her upbringing in Bangladesh, her parents' marriage, and her early relationship with her husband. She also talks at length about her lifelong involvement in dance and the fine arts, including both her personal passion and the role they play in maintaining younger generations of Bengali Americans' connection to their cultural and religious heritage. In addition, she speaks about her involvement in the Bangladesh Institute of Performing Arts and local community groups, as well as her desire to see more women in her community become socially engaged outside the home. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Bangladeshis -- Cultural assimilation; Folk dancing, Bangladeshi; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam and the performing arts; Islamic education of children -- New York (State) -- New York (State); Women in community organization -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women in Islam; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Dhaka (Bangladesh); Kensington (New York, N.Y.); Bangladesh Institute of Performing Arts (Queens, New York, N.Y.); Ferdous, Annie
- Oral History Interview with Idris Conry, June 21, 2018; 2018.006.22
  Idris Conry was born in 1952 in Brooklyn. He graduated from Boys' High School in Brooklyn and briefly played football for Shaw University in Raleigh, North Carolina before earning his bachelor of the arts in African American studies from John Jay College in Manhattan. He and his wife both embraced Islam in the 1970s and worshipped first at Masjid Ikhwa in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn and then at Masjid At-Taqwa in Bedford-Stuyvesant. In 2001, he opened Abu Baker's Bakery (now known as Abu's Homestyle Bakery) next door to Masjid At-Taqwa. The bakery is currently managed by his son, Idris Braithwaite (interviewed for this collection on July 7, 2018).
  In this interview, Idris Conry discusses his family, his education at Boys High School in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, and his semester-long scholarship to Shaw University in Raleigh, North Carolina. He talks extensively about his Muslim faith and identity, including his initial exposure to the religion through his Muslim stepfather, his decision to embrace Islam, and his perspective on cultural traditions within the Muslim African American community. He also elaborates on his experiences at specific mosques, especially regarding Imam Khalid Yasin's leadership at Masjid Ikhwa in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn and community policing efforts by Masjid At-Taqwa in Bedford-Stuyvesant. In addition, he speaks about opening Abu Baker's Bakery (now known as Abu's Homestyle Bakery) next door to Masjid At-Taqwa, the bakery's focus on bean pies and their significance to the Muslim African American community, and future plans for the bakery. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  African American college athletes -- United States; African American cooking; African American Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; African American universities and college -- North Carolina -- Raleigh; Bakeries -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Black Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community policing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Family-owned business enterprises -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Food -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Islam -- Customs and practices; Islamic education of children -- New York (State) -- New York (State); Music -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim converts -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Prospect Park (New York, N.Y.); Abu's Homestyle Bakery (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Bears Football Team (Shaw University); Boys' High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Masjid At-Taqwa (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Masjid Ikhwa (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Braithwaite, Idris; Conry, Idris; Yasin, Khalid
- Oral History Interview with Idris Braithwaite, July 7, 2018
  Idris Braithwaite was born in 1971 in Brooklyn. He had a strong interest in dance and music from a young age, including attending his father's music rehearsals and working as a DJ. As an adult, he served on the Bedford-Stuyvesant Gateway Business Improvement District Board, founded the non-profit Aunt and Uncle Youth Employment Services, and took over management of Abu's Homestyle Bakery (originally known as Abu Baker's Bakery) in 2011 from his father, Idris Conry (interviewed for this collection on June 21, 2018).
  In this interview, Idris Braithwaite discusses his childhood in Brooklyn, being raised in a Muslim household following his parents' conversion to Islam from Christianity, and his approach to educating his own children about Islam. He also talks about his relationship with his African American and Muslim identities, including the distinction he draws between Muslim beliefs and Arab culture. In addition, he speaks extensively about his father's founding of Abu Baker's Bakery (now known as Abu's Homestyle Bakery) in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn in 2001 and his own management of the bakery starting in 2011, especially regarding the bakery's focus on bean pies and their significance to the Muslim African American community. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  African American cooking; African American Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bakeries -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Clothing and dress -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Family-owned business enterprises -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Food -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Islam -- Customs and practices; Islamic religious education; Music -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim families -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Religion and ethics; Small business marketing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Braithwaite, Idris; Conry, Idris; Abu's Homestyle Bakery (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Wazina Zondon, August 2, 2018; 2018.006.24
  Wazina Zondon was born in 1982 in the Flushing neighborhood of Queens. She began working as a sexuality educator while attending the State University of New York at New Paltz. She continued her work in the field after graduating, including with the Planned Parenthood in Newburgh, New York; the Empire State Pride Agenda in New York City; and the Urban Assembly Institute for Math and Science for Young Women in the Downtown Brooklyn neighborhood of Brooklyn. She also co-wrote and performed the series Coming Out Muslim: Radical Acts of Love, which was inspired by her experiences as a queer Muslim woman.
  In this interview, Wazina Zondon discusses her family, growing up in the Flushing neighborhood of Queens, and attending the State University of New York at New Paltz for college. She speaks extensively about her identity as a Muslim Afghan queer woman; her work with Terna Tilley-Gyado on their performance series Coming Out Muslim: Radical Acts of Love; and their collaboration on the project with musician Alsarah Abunama-Elgadi (interviewed for this collection on August 31, 2018). She also talks about working as a sex educator, especially in New York City public schools; moving to the Crown Heights and Flatbush neighborhoods of Brooklyn; and her concerns about gentrification. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  Afghan Americans -- New York (State); Children of immigrants -- New York (State) -- Queens; Coming out (Sexual orientation); Cultural pluralism -- New York (State); Feminism; Gentrification -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam and the performing arts; Muslim educators -- New York (State); Muslim families -- New York (State) -- Queens; Queer culture; Queer identity; Political activists -- New York (State) -- New York; Religion and culture; Religious pluralism -- New York (State); Sex educators -- New York (State); Women in Islam; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Flushing (New York, N.Y.); Queens (New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Fahiym Abdul-Wasi, August 7, 2018; 2018.006.25
  Fahiym Abdul-Wasi was born in 1973 in New York City. He grew up in the Bedford-Stuyvesant and Crown Heights neighborhoods of Brooklyn. He explored different Muslim traditions throughout his teenage and adult years, including the Five Percent Nation, the Ansaaru Allah Community, the Nation of Islam, and Sufism. His work as a hip-hop journalist was featured in a variety of publications and he served as the editor-in-chief of the music magazine The Source under the byline Joshua Fahiym Ratcliffe.
  In this interview, Fahiym Abdul-Wasi discusses his childhood in Brooklyn, his education, and his social life. He speaks at length about his experiences with religion, including his involvement with the Jehovah's Witnesses as a child and his exploration of different traditions of Islam, including the Five Percent Nation, the Ansaaru Allah Community, the Nation of Islam, and Sufism. He expands on his memories of Muhammad Mosque No. 7 in the Harlem neighborhood of Manhattan and the police standoff that occurred there in 1994. He also talks extensively about his work as a hip-hop journalist, particularly with regards to the music magazine The Source. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  Black Muslims -- New York (State) -- New York; Caribbean Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Education of children -- New York (State) -- New York; Hip-hop -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Interfaith families -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam -- Customs and practices; Jehovah's Witnesses -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Journalists -- New York (State) -- New York; Muslims converts from Christianity -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslims, Black -- New York (State) -- New York; Nuwaubian movement -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Police-community relations -- New York (State) -- New York; Rap (Music) -- Periodicals; Religious pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Sufism; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bushwick (New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Five Percent Nation
- Oral History Interview with Nsenga Knight, August 7, 2018; 2018.006.26
  Nsenga Knight was born in 1981 in the East Flatbush neighborhood of Brooklyn. As a child, her family attended mosques in the nearby Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, including both Masjid At-Taqwa and Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah. As an adult, she became active in New York's fine arts community, creating both exhibitions and performances that explore various facets of her identity as a Black and Muslim woman in the United States. Her formal education included both a bachelor of the fine arts from Howard University in Washington, D.C. and a master of the fine arts from the University of Pennsylvania in Philadelphia. She moved to Egypt in 2017.
  In this interview, Nsenga Knight remembers her childhood experiences with Islam, including attending Masjid At-Taqwa and Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah, both in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn; learning martial arts at a local academy run by members of the Nation of Islam; celebrating Eids in Prospect Park; and her mother's conversion to Islam. She also speaks about the value placed on physical strength within her African American Muslim communities. In addition, she extensively discusses her involvement in the arts, especially regarding her performance art at the University of Pennsylvania in Philadelphia, exhibitions done with the She Shootin' Photography Collective, and memories of her broader friend group of Muslim artists and scholars. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  Artists, Black -- United States; Black Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Communities -- Religious aspects -- Muslims; Food -- Social aspects -- New York (State) -- Kings County; ʻĪd al-Aḍḥā -- New York (State) -- Kings County; ʻĪd al-Fiṭr -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam -- Customs and practices; Islam and art -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Martial arts -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Muslim artists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim converts from Christianity -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslims, Black -- United States; Performance art -- Pennsylvania -- Philadelphia; Self-defense -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Women artists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); East Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Park (New York, N.Y.); Women in Islam -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Masjid At-Taqwa (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); She Shootin' Photography Collective (New York, N.Y.); University of Pennsylvania. School of Design; Knight, Nsenga
- Oral History Interview with Rodney Adib Rashid, August 14, 2018; 2018.006.27
  Rodney Adib Rashid was born in 1955 in Christiansted, United States Virgin Islands. His family moved to Brooklyn two years later. He embraced the Nation of Islam in the early 1970s and adopted Warith Deen Mohammed's reforms to the tradition following Elijah Muhammad's death in 1975. He attended Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn in the 1980s, becoming the mosque's imam in 1989. Under his leadership, the mosque emphasized community outreach and education, including holding Eids in Prospect Park; improving the safety of the neighborhood around Masjid Khalifah; and opening the Clara Muhammad of Masjid Khalifah school, which was run by his wife Darlene Bashir (interviewed for this collection on September 10, 2018).
  In this interview, Rodney Adib Rashid discusses growing up on the island of Saint Croix in the United States Virgin Islands and in New York City. He mentions getting in trouble with the law as a teenager in New York and speaks at length about about his exploration of Islam while incarcerated, particularly regarding his interactions with other Muslim prisoners and involvement in the Nation of Islam. He elaborates on his continued study of Warith Deen Mohammed's teachings after his release, especially as imam of Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. He also talks about Masjid Khalifah's history, its growth in the thirty years that he has been its imam, his hopes for the mosque's future, and the ongoing gentrification of Bedford-Stuyvesant. He also touches on his first marriage and his life immediately after being released from prison. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  African American Muslims -- New York (State) -- New York; Black Muslims -- New York (State) -- New York; Feasts and Fasts -- Islam; Gentrification -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Imams (Mosque officers) -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islamic religious education -- United States; Muslim converts -- United States; Prisoners -- Religious life -- United States; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Saint Croix (United States Virgin Islands); Masjid Abdul Muhsi Khalifah (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Muhammad Mosque No. 7C (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Shafaiat Ali, August 27, 2018; 2018.006.28
  Shafaiat Ali was born in 1948 in Trinidad and Tobago. He immigrated to the United States in 1968 and settled in Brooklyn. He married his wife, who also emigrated from Trinidad and Tobago, in 1971. They opened Ali's Trinidad Roti Shop in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn in the late 1970s. They have since expanded the restaurant, which was one of the first in Brooklyn to serve Caribbean halal food.
  In this interview, Shafaiat Ali discusses his family, his immigration to the United States, and his marriage to his wife. He speaks at length about his ownership of Ali's Trinidad Roti Shop in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, the restaurant's strong focus on Caribbean food, and community support for the restaurant. He also talks about changes in Bedford-Stuyvesant since he opened the shop in the 1970s, including the development of Fulton Street's commercial businesses and efforts by members of the nearby Masjid At-Taqwa to reduce crime in neighborhood in the late 1980s. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  Community policing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Cooking, Trinidadian; Family-owned business enterprises -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Food -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Halal food -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Restaurants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Trinidadians -- New York (State) -- Kings County; West Indian Americans -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Ali's Trinidad Roti Shop (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Masjid At-Taqwa (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Beatrice Sabir, August 28, 2018; 2018.006.29